<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<sect1
	xml:id="been.user.execution.csvcs"
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xmlns:xml="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace"
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook ../../../docbook-5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
>
	<title>Core BEEN Services</title>

	<para>BEEN includes several services of key importance. This section lists
	these core services and instructs user where to find more information about them.</para>
	
	<sect2>
		<title>Software Repository</title>
		<para>
		Software Repository is a component that stores BEEN packages containing tasks, pluggable 
		modules and possibly also other types of packages. It has an interface through which
		these packages can be searched for, uploaded and downloaded.
		</para>
		<para>
		Software Repository can be started from "Services" tab of WebUI and controlled
		from "Software Repository" tab.
		</para>
		<para>
		More information about Software Repository you can find in Development Documentation,
		<xref linkend="been.devel.sr"/>
		</para>
	</sect2>
	
	<sect2>
		<title>Host Manager</title>
		<para>This section has been copied from <biblioref linkend="BUD2" units="page" begin="24"/>.</para>
		<para>The Host Manager is responsible for maintaining an up-to-date list of all hosts in the
		benchmarking environment and maintains database which stores data about hardware and
		software configuration of each host.</para>
		<para>The Host Manager is also responsible for monitoring availability and utilization of hosts in the
		environment. It provides tools to generate basic statistics about the utilization of a specific
		host over time.</para>
	</sect2>
	
	<sect2>
		<title>Debug Assistant</title>
		<para>
		Debug Assistant is a service that simplifies debugging
		of tasks run by BEEN. It can be started from "Services" tab of WebUI
		and controlled from "Debug Assistant" tab. 
		</para>
		<para>
		More information about debugging BEEN and tasks run by it you can 
		find in <xref linkend="been.devel.theory.debug"/>.
		</para>	
	</sect2>
	
	
	<sect2>
		<title>Results Repository</title>
		<para>
		The Results Repository service can be started from "Services" tab
		of WebUI.
		</para>
		<para>
		Detailed information about how to use Results Repository
		can be found in Development Documentation, <xref linkend="been.devel.rrng"/>
		 and User Documentation, <xref linkend="been.user.benchmark.results"/>.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	
	<sect2>
		<title>Benchmark Manager</title>
		<para>The Benchmark Manager service can be started from "Services" tab
		of WebUI.</para>
		<para>
		Detailed information about how to use Benchmark Manager
		can be found in Development Documentation, <xref linkend="been.devel.bmng"/>
		 and User Documentation, <xref linkend="been.user.benchmark"/>.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	
	<sect2>
		<title>Command Line Interface</title>
		<para>
		The Command Line Interface service can be started from "Services" tab
		of WebUI.
		</para>
		<para>
		Detailed information about how to use Command Line Interface
		can be found in Development Documentation, <xref linkend="been.devel.cli"/>
		 and User Documentation, <xref linkend="been.user.cli"/>.
		</para>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
