<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<sect1
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xmlns:xml="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace"
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook ../../../docbook-5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
>
	<title>Purpose</title>

	<para>
The <glossterm>Benchmark Manager</glossterm> is a <glossterm>service</glossterm> for managing <glossterm>analyses</glossterm>. It stores their meta data and handles their scheduling. It provides basic functions to create, run once or periodically, update and delete analyses. It was designed to replace the legacy Benchmark Manager of BEEN.
	</para>

	<para>
	New Benchmark Manager is designed to be light-weight and flexible component. We replaced old, rather big plug-ins which always contained <classname>Configurator</classname>, <classname>Generator</classname> and <classname>VersionProvider</classname> classes. Now we use smaller specialized <glossterm>generator</glossterm> and <glossterm>evaluator</glossterm> <glossterm baseform="pluggable module">pluggable modules</glossterm> to separate the creation and evaluation of benchmark data. These pluggable modules are commonly called BMmodules as they are generally not used by anyone else but the Benchmark Manager.
	</para>

	<sect2>
		<title>Framework Integration</title>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
				<glossterm>Command Line Interface</glossterm> and web interface modules provide user interface to the Benchmark Manager. They both use <interfacename>BenchmarkManagerInterface</interfacename> to display data about analyses. They also use <interfacename>BenchmarkManagerCallbackInterface</interfacename> to allow user to manually mark some analysis runs as finished (which is usually <glossterm>context-monitor</glossterm>'s job).
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
				The <glossterm>generator-runner</glossterm> <glossterm>task</glossterm> uses <interfacename>BenchmarkManagerCallbackInterface</interfacename> to report that analysis tasks have been generated.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
				The <glossterm>context-monitor</glossterm> task (created by the <glossterm>generator-runner</glossterm>) uses <interfacename>BenchmarkManagerCallbackInterface</interfacename> to report end of analysis run.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
				Benchmark Manager uses <classname>PluggableModuleManager</classname> to load used pluggable modules.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
				It also uses JAXB configuration parser to read the BMmodules' configuration description.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
				Benchmark Manager and <glossterm>generator-runner</glossterm> use <glossterm>Task Manager</glossterm> to plan new <glossterm>analysis run</glossterm>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
				There is also connection to the <glossterm>Results Repository</glossterm> through generator and evaluator pluggable modules which might need to create some <glossterm>datasets</glossterm> and <glossterm>triggers</glossterm> in the Results Repository.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect2>

	<sect2>
		<title>Classification</title>

		<para>
		This component consists of:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
				A single BEEN <glossterm>service</glossterm> - <classname>BenchmarkManagerService</classname> and <classname>BenchmarkManagerImplementation</classname>
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
				Two tasks - <glossterm>generator-runner</glossterm> (Benchmark Manager specific) and <glossterm>context-monitor</glossterm> (which can be used for other purposes)
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
				Several meta data objects (<classname>Analysis</classname>, <classname>AnalysisState</classname>, <classname>BMmodule</classname>, ...)
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
				Attached (pluggable) BMmodules can also be considered part of Benchmark Manager although they can be removed or added even on runtime.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

	</sect2>
</sect1>
