<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<sect1
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xmlns:xml="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace"
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook ../../../docbook-5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
>
	<title>Scripting Basics</title>
	
	<para>
	Scripting a powerful tool that allows BEEN to be extended more easily by
	allowing user to use code written not only in Java, but also in languages
	that are believed to make development more effective for some types of tasks. 
	Currently BEEN supports scripts in two languages: Python and Shell scripts.
	Both of these languages have some advantages and disadvantages and will
	take a closer look on them later in this chapter.  
	</para>
	
	
	<sect2>
	<title>Scripting Languages</title>

		<sect3>
		<title>Jython Scripting</title>
		<para>
			Jython is pure Java scripting language fully compatible 
			with Python. In addition to Python compatibility, Jython
			is also Java compatible (Jython script can import java classes
			and call java methods as if they were written in Python). 			
			As a result, you can write Python scripts
			that will be executed as BEEN <glossterm>tasks</glossterm> and from these script
			you can still easily interact with BEEN environment
			just as from regular BEEN task written in Java.
		</para>
		</sect3>
	
		<sect3>
		<title>Shell Scripting</title>	
		<para>
			Another scripting language supported by BEEN is
			platform dependent shell. BEEN's ability to 
			execute <glossterm>shell scripts can</glossterm> be very useful for example
			when you have a lot of build scripts you want to 
			use in your benchmarks. 
		</para>
		<para>
			From their nature, <glossterm>shell scripts</glossterm> are platform dependent.
			This means, whenever you're running a shell script as
			a <glossterm>task</glossterm>, you should be aware which platform
			is that script running on and supply a script
			that is compatible with that platform (so you
			supply a Bash script for Linux host or Windows script
			for host running of Windows).
		</para>
		</sect3>
	</sect2>
	
	
</sect1>