<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<sect1
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xmlns:xml="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace"
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook ../../../docbook-5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
>
	<title>Quick start guide</title>

	<para>
	Basic knowledge about building java applications and managing Apache Tomcat server is expected in this chapter. This method worked on most of the systems and distributions we tried, however it is not guaranteed to work everywhere. Please consult the regular instalation manual if this guide does not work for you.
	</para>

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			Download source from svn://svn.forge.objectweb.org/svnroot/been/trunk.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			Build the source using ant dist.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			Coppy the directory dist/full to the machine where the Task Manager will run. Coppy the directory dist/hostruntime to all the machines where only Host Runtime will run.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			Run the Task Manager using either taskmanager.sh or taskmanager.bat in the full/bin directory. Run your first Host Runtime using either hostruntime.sh or hostruntime.bat in the same directory.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			Run the additional Host Runtimes on other computers in your network using the appropriate hostruntime script in the hostruntime/bin directory. You have to enter the Task Manager host name as a parameter this time.
				<cmdsynopsis>
					<command>hostruntime</command>
					<arg><replaceable>Task Manager host</replaceable></arg>
				</cmdsynopsis>
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			Deploy dist/been.war to your Apache Tomcat server either through the Administration page or manually. Set the Task Manager host in the configuration tab if the Apache Tomcat server is running on different host.
			</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>To run an example analysis through the web interface follow these steps:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			Start BEEN and the core services (host manager, software repository, benchmark manager, results repository)
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			Go to benchmarks -&gt; create analysis and select simpletest generator, fill in name and scheduling period
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			If you want to see work of evaluators, select simpletest evaluator on the first page and Results Repository on the generator configration page.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			All the settings not listed here can be omited.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			Ater finishing the wizard, you can sit back and watch BEEN work.
			</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

</sect1>
